[Music]
welcome back to the real news network
uh reality asserts itself and i'm with
john kiriakou
and he and i were started arguing as we
were waiting for the cameras to go back
on i said wait a second let's turn them
on and let's argue
for real in front of the cameras and
what we're arguing about
is i'm saying i think there's evidence i
can't
say it's proven or definitive but i
think in a normal court of law you could
get somebody
charged with the amount of evidence
there is at least you could get an
indictment whether you get a conviction
or not i don't know
that someone very senior in the white
house and from what we know the someone
is likely to be
vice president richard cheney and please
mr cheney please sue me for libel i
would love to have this out in court
uh so please if if by any chance you're
watching
um there's there is evidence
that the intelligence agencies in the
united states were
more or less told to stand down when it
comes to
fighting terrorism richard clark is
demoted george tenet tells the
the white house in a presidential uh his
first bush's first presidential briefing
bin laden and uh al qaeda is the number
one threat to uh
national security and in fact what
happens is this
terrorism and the security that security
threat is demoted fbi is told
not to prioritize terrorism john told us
in the summer
that the head of the countertel
terrorism unit the cia
told him that they were expecting
something massive coming
cannot get condoleezza rice to listen um
so i'm saying this
ain't just not listening and it isn't
just an intelligence failure and john
says
hi john go ahead i'm no fan of dick
cheney i never was
i think he's a malignant force in the
history of our country
but i just can't believe that someone
who is charged with running our country
would be so psychopathic as to
encourage a massive attack i mean i
it just doesn't make any kind of logical
sense to me
i can tell you that at the cia we were
never told to stand down
while we certainly needed a greater
counter-terrorism budget
we were doing everything humanly
possible
to try to infiltrate al qaeda in 2001
and to try to disrupt this
attack that we knew was coming but you
had good information
we had some information we're getting it
in bits and pieces and the analysts put
it together
and and decided that that uh bin laden
was determined to attack the united
states don't you think you had enough to
tell immigration to be extra strict
don't you think he had enough
to maybe take a long a closer look at
saudi immigration don't you think get
the federal agencies and authorities
should have been sure but you're talking
about security threat level but you're
talking about policy changes
and you know it's a fact of life in the
united states we're a big
lumbering bureaucracy and policy changes
can take months or years but this goes
back to this
belief of yours that you cannot believe
that a leader of the united states would
allow something like this to happen but
i also don't think that he had the power
to do something like that
the the bureaucracy is just simply too
vast
and and cheney was powerful but he
wasn't powerful enough
to single-handedly stop the wheels of
the intelligence community and allow
uh al-qaeda into the country to launch
an attack can you give me another
explanation how condoleezza rice doesn't
listen when the cia says something
massive is coming
maybe condoleezza rice was an
incompetent boob i mean there's that
school of thought too
because you can't believe it all goes to
a question of faith underlying it sure
if you were a cop looking at a murderer
and you just had this as straightforward
evidence
or a cia analyst if it wasn't a leader
of the united states
i can't believe you would you just can't
what i'm suggesting there's evidence of
is not a massive conspiracy
i agree with you i think a massive
conspiracy is impossible
to keep covered uh i'm suggesting
that someone very senior like vice
president cheney
understands the way the american
bureaucracy works and he knows
if you de-prioritize if you
don't take any extra measures to make
sure the agencies are talking to each
other
like let's go another way what you could
have done osama bin laden plans to
attack united states
oh oh let's get all the heads of
agencies that might have anything to do
with us in a meeting and say jesus are
we prepared just in case something is
coming here
oh cia is saying something massive is
coming and put that together what the
cia just told us that it might be in the
united states
conde don't you think you better get
clark and
get tenant in here and get the fbi and
maybe who else you need
and and make sure you guys are actually
talking to each other about stuff
i mean if you were running a hamburger
stand that's what you would do
that's what you would do yes i agree and
cheney ain't stupid
you know george ain't stupid but he's
not as bright as cheney is
not to do that suggests perhaps
it's a decision not to do that i'll
agree with you with you that it's
certainly worth investigating and there
wasn't an adequate and appropriate
investigation
let's go back a step let's go back a
step you know the story how richard
nixon
sabotaged lyndon johnson's peace talks
with the north shore
sure because of nixon perhaps
hundreds of thousands of vietnamese and
cambodians died
because of he sabotaged those talks now
maybe they would have fallen apart
anyway
maybe but we do know and we have it from
the johnson library the actual audio
tape where lyndon johnson says
nixon is acting like a traitor some of
our folks
including some of the old china lobby
are going to the vietnamese embassy
and saying please notify the president
that he'll hold out to november the 2nd
they could get a better deal
now i'm reading their hand over i don't
want to get this in the campaign
and they ought to be doing this this is
treason now there's the president of the
united states i mean
about to be president of the united
states acting like a traitor
sabotaging what might have been a peace
agreement
for his own agenda so how is that any
different than what i'm suggesting so
here's a leader of the united states
that was willing to do that
but i'm not sure he was willing to do
that i'm again i'm not defending dick
cheney
i'm just not ascribing to him these
supernatural powers
to to allow a terrorist group into the
united states something supernatural
just
demote richard clark tell writers that
was a political decision
to demote richard clark maybe then as we
said then get rid of richard clark if
you don't like richard clark
firemen replace him with someone you
like don't demote the odds it was my
understanding
that richard clark asked to stay on the
national security council
and they created the cyber security czar
position for him
later immediately he moved directly from
one job into the other
he moved directly from counter-terrorism
into cyber security but when his hair is
on fire
and condoleezza rice won't listen to
their the
cia when they say something massive is
coming
their counter-terrorisms are something's
massive is coming this can't just be
incompetence
at least it should be investigated i
know you're gonna get that i agree with
i agree it should be this is your
underlying faith that uh that a leader
of the united states would never do such
a thing to not
americans no i don't think so i i just i
i
can't believe it it's too much
all right let's move on okay um where
are you on 9 11
i was in cia headquarters on 9 11. i was
supposed to go downtown with
kopha black to see condoleezza rice uh
on an issue related to greek
uh terrorism and um i i had
gotten a call that our car was ready uh
to take us downtown so i walked over to
cofer's office
and just outside his office his
secretary was sitting and she was
watching tv
and one of the towers of the world trade
center was burning and i said
what happened to the world trade center
and she said a plane flew into it
and me not really giving it much thought
said
or i should i should say i'm not giving
it much thought
said you know that happened in the 1930s
a plane flew into the empire state
building
but it was really foggy then and it's so
clear today how can you not see that
you're flying into the world trade
center
and as i said that the second plane flew
into
tower one and neither one of us reacted
and finally she turned to me
she was sitting down i was standing
behind her and she said did you see that
it was as though our brains couldn't
even register
what we had just seen so i ran back to
my office
and i told my colleagues guys i think
we're under attack
two planes just hit both towers of the
world trade center
we turned on the tv and then the
pentagon was hit
so everybody gathered in this huge
office that is the cia's
counter-terrorism center
there were tvs mounted from the ceiling
hanging down on poles this is like in
twenty four the two yeah
kind of a room like that kind of yeah
great big open we called it a cubicle
farm
must have had 300 cubicles in it so
we're all gathered around watching the
towers burn
watching the pentagon burn and then
finally
somebody in the back of the crowd shouts
will somebody please
lead and that was like
it was as though somebody had shaken
cover and he snapped out of it
and started barking orders you go to the
director's office you go to security you
go here you go there
and then he says everybody else evacuate
and we just stood there and i heard a
couple people say i'm not going anywhere
this is what we've been working for all
this time and so
it wasn't until individual cia policemen
came to the office and said everybody
evacuate
evacuate or we're going to cuff you and
walk you to your cars
we all evacuated so
i drove to i was driving back to my
apartment and the way i got there was
on the george washington parkway from
the cia parking lot just straight
down toward washington and traffic was
so bad i just abandoned my car
i walked the rest of the way i actually
saw a couple
of people that i knew one was a former
cia officer
who were working at the white house at
the national security council and they
had even abandoned the white house
and they were walking back to their own
houses and apartments
so i met my then girlfriend now
wife uh at my apartment uh we
went up to the roof and watched the
pentagon burn for a little while and
then we went out and tried to donate
blood
but the lines were so long that it was
just impossible to donate blood
and i said to her this is ridiculous we
need to go back to work
she was a cia officer too so we walked
back to my car
on the gw parkway got in the car went
back to headquarters and then i didn't
leave for four days
just slept under my desk i would ball up
my jacket and use that as a pillow
a couple of officers took some bolt
cutters and
and cut the chain off the the doors to
the cafeteria
we went in and stole all the food we
cooked it ourselves and just put it on
on folding tables out in the hallway so
people who were working 24 hours
would have something to eat i think we
ended up writing a check to the marriott
for like
10 or 15 000 to replace all the food
that we took
but nobody left everybody stayed see
when you say the cia was working as hard
as it could
just to prevent it i'm also sure the cia
was working as hard as it could to find
capture or kill bin laden i see no
reason to think
they weren't trying they were um
but there was a great debate at the time
not in mainstream news because you
couldn't get
get heard on mainstream news but amongst
people who
were from the region as well as people
here that were critics of
going to massive war in afghanistan to
start with
that this could have been more of a
black ops operation there could have
been a real
laser focus on finding and dealing with
al qaeda and bin laden
there didn't need to be regime change
and all-out war in afghanistan
um were you aware of that debate or
argument and and why
why it wasn't even in retrospect why
wasn't the strategy that
in in retrospect it's my understanding
that
for example the navy seals of 2015
are absolutely nothing like the navy
seals of 2001.
it it's my understanding that that
we just didn't have the the wherewithal
in 2001 to be able to not
just locate uh bin laden i mean we
essentially knew he was somewhere in the
torah borah area
uh he was probably in that camp but
we weren't certain um not just that but
then to physically go in and get him
i'm just not sure that we could have
done something like that in 2001.
i'm not a military analyst so what were
you what were you focused on
in those two three weeks after 9 11 what
was your assignment it was mostly name
traces
you know around the world in every
every american embassy around the world
people began
walking in and saying i have information
on al qaeda
and they would give us these names well
there were
tens of thousands of names sometimes
thousands coming in every day and we
needed an
army of clerks is what it amounted to
to search all of our databases looking
at information pertaining to these names
i was in kandahar
in the spring of 2002 making a film
called return to kandahar
and told by numerous people and i what
i'm about to say i have no idea what the
meaning of it is i can't draw any
conclusion from it
but numerous people in kandahar told me
that about
something in a week and a half seven
eight nine days after 9 11.
mula omar and bin laden and everybody
knows where they live
which is this is another thing which
makes no sense to me everybody knew
where bin laden's compound was they had
you know there's like 30 20 30 white
suvs coming in and out all day long
that they leave in the middle of daytime
omar's
big trail of white suvs bin laden's
trail of white suvs and they drive to
toribura
and nothing happens but i'm not trying
to suggest i know what that means
we didn't have armed drones at the time
um and we didn't have
i mean you the the intelligence has to
be so immediate
which really almost never happens in the
intelligence world it has to be so
immediate and you have to have planes in
the sky
ready to receive the the intelligence to
be able to act that quickly
seven days later you don't have somebody
on the ground in canada no
how do you get into kandahar i mean you
have to have a sponsor somebody's got to
be there to protect you
and to give you cover you can't just you
know go rent a hotel room and
start looking for bin laden i watch tv
somebody
you get a woman gets in a burka and she
can walk anywhere she wants no
and there's no such thing as a live
satellite feed either you see that in tv
all the time
where people are saying i need a i need
a live satellite feed now and then they
watch the guy
walk through the streets of a city that
just there's no such thing
then or now even now there's no such
thing but now it'd be drones
now it would be drunk you're saying
there's no camera on a satellite that
watches everything yes
well that's good to know i suppose um
all right so you're doing this name
search and
um what do you make of the strategy in
afghanistan you know this
i mean it was a very strange moment once
the all-out attack
starts on the taliban they're bombing
the hell out of kabul
they run out of things to bomb and they
keep bombing because they have to prove
they're doing something i guess i don't
they think american public opinion
demands revenge i don't know what it is
but the northern alliance all the old
warlords that actually
made such a mess in afghanistan that it
helped create the conditions for the
rise of the taliban in the first place
they may have killed me some people
think as many as two million people
right in the civil war between who's
gonna
who's gonna be the and now one of them
is the vice president
of afghanistan yeah we'll get to that i
dost them
uh and then then they decide you know
okay
they being the white house the pentagon
they decide okay we're gonna make the
deal with the warlords
and they you know shovel millions and
millions of dollars into the pockets of
these
essentially war criminals and that's and
that's the strategy for afghanistan
i think you have some of the timing
wrong though uh first
gary schroen who was a very senior cia
officer legendary officer
wrote a book called first in and it's
about how he
and a and a small team of cia special
operations officers were the first cia
group in
afghanistan and they went on something
like september 12th
so they were they were in the north with
uh
his name escapes me now the one that was
killed in the bombing the day before
september
with massoud's people uh later on with
dustin's people but there was a cia
presence
in afghanistan from the days immediately
following
the the uh attacks the september 11th
attacks
uh there's an old saying about afghan
warlords
that you can't buy an afghan warlord but
you can certainly rent one
and that's the cia way the cia way is to
throw
massive amounts of money uh at a problem
and hope that some of it sticks
and some of it stuck now was it a
success
ah probably not in the long run but at
least
it bought us some time when i say that
it wasn't a success
what i mean is instead of these warlords
capturing senior al-qaeda leaders and
turning them over to us
we ended up filling guantanamo and other
places
with you know largely innocent nobodies
who had been turned in uh by their
neighbors for a bounty
or who wanted to settle scores with
people they didn't like
but it it did buy us some time it put
the taliban on the run
remember we didn't start bombing
afghanistan for almost a month
we we wanted to give
omar a chance to turn bin laden over to
us
and i really believe that if he had done
that
al-qaeda would have imploded as an
organization
and we would never have had any reason
to go to war in afghanistan and there's
pretty good evidence
that and i i told you off-camera i'll
tell the story again
quickly i interviewed a former member of
the taliban central council
at muhammad karzai's brother wally
karzai who himself was assassinated just
a few years ago
in his living room were all on carpets
in the living room
and he says that there was a there was a
meeting of the taliban central council
called by mullah omar to debate whether
or not to hand over bin laden and they
vote that they will hand over bin laden
another meeting is called three days
later and according to this guy
he says it's the pakistani foreign
minister that's how it was translated
and we have all this on tape came to the
meeting and talked them out of handing
over bin laden
um the the
they're still the grounds and i go back
to my my original question there's still
a place there
where the strategy could have been
focused on al qaeda bin laden even
mullah omar
if you have evidence he was connected to
it and there's i think
there seems to be there seems some it
doesn't
necessarily call for an awa war in
afghanistan and regime change
oh i think you're probably right first i
i think that the story is probably
correct
i i i can't imagine what benefit
the the taliban central council could
possibly have
thought there would be to
allowing bin laden to remain in in
afghanistan that just doesn't make any
any sense and from all indications omar
although uneducated is very very bright
and certainly
he's a great political strategist
at least he was so i think the story you
heard is probably
correct i'm not sure that we could have
that we could have disrupted
destroyed al qaeda without an all-out
war without the
the cooperation of the taliban i think
that we were
kind of pushed into it
now was there was there a pakistani uh
conspiracy
it's very possible now we're going to
get into that quite a bit the pakistani
sites the only reason i'm holding the
back on that right now okay
because your next stop is pakistan so
i'm going to kind of wait to talk about
the pakistani part what i'm getting at
what i think is even more important
though
is the the strategy of allying with
warlords
and essentially handing over the poppy
crops
of afghanistan as part of the deal
because that's really what happens in
afghanistan
afghanistan poppy production was not nil
but next to
next one year under the taliban into the
taliban for one year
they produced 90 percent of the world's
uh
heroin poppy under the taliban it went
down to zero
for a year and then back up to 90
percent again
i did a long in-depth study on this when
i was with the senate foreign relations
committee yeah
i wouldn't argue with you heroin poppy
was was the way the taliban earned its
money that's how they could
afford all of their weaponry you i can't
i don't know anything to disagree with
you and i don't know why i would
uh but my point was this gets handed
over to the warlords oh yeah
millions and millions of dollars in
suitcases this enormous poppy crop
and then some because i think it gets
far far bigger once the northern
alliance warlord types take over it
could be we estimated that
that afghanistan now produces 93 of the
world's heroin
and all of that heroin is produced by
people with ties to the various warlords
so as a strategy you're handing the
country
essentially over to war criminals and
drug lords
over here we're hearing democracy we're
invading afghanistan for women
and one i'm the only one that seems to
remember this and i don't know why
because nobody ever talks about this but
me
president bush went on television and
asked every child in america to donate
one dollar
towards children in afghanistan it was
going to be this big
program children to children program
last week i asked america's children
to send a dollar to the white house to
help provide food and medicine to the
children
of afghanistan and i'm still asking
where's the money i'm sure some kids
sent dollars in and
no one ever heard another word about
this send a dollar
to save an afghan kid jeez i hadn't
heard that
it was on tv i guess i was focused on
work it's just this is a strategy
which we now know was really all about
the lead up to war in iraq
but they didn't they really didn't have
much strategy for afghanistan other than
do something make a show of it
assuming i don't know how they assumed i
guess the warlords will take over
afghanistan and look after it for us and
everything will be fine the taliban will
run away
and we're going to go and and and
tiptoe through the daisies in iraq i
don't disagree with that
it's insane i think that there was
always a plan to attack iraq
always from before george w bush even
won the presidency i think that there
was a
that there was a um a movement among
prominent neoconservatives in this
country to come up with a plan
so that when and if george w bush won
the presidency
they could pitch this plan to attack
iraq and they could
disguise it in any way they wanted uh
911 i think was
the most convenient way to do it and for
them the easiest way to try
it's it's it's it's so insane
it's so delusional like i i know like
i've interviewed ray mcgovern and some
other
you know former cia guys i mean you guys
are sitting there trying to do real
analysis
based on evidence and foreign policy is
being made i i don't know what else
mr cheney you're a sociopath like please
sue me please i want a chance
to prove it the foreign policy is being
made by sociopaths connected with what
military-industrial complex a vision of
a pax americana i mean all of the above
all of the above yes
i think that's right and i always
believed too that that the animosity
between the bush white house and
and saddam hussein was was very personal
and that it was
because of saddam's attempt to
assassinate president george h.w
bush in kuwait in 1993. i always
believed that was the root
and we have another series of interviews
we're going to be releasing soon with a
historian named happy
and he about vietnam and he has a very
interesting quota i may have quoted
earlier in our interviews here but
that vietnam by the last year or two
completely
became about proving the strength of
america oh absolutely
and no other real objectives other than
that
what else was iraq the same thing
it's the same thing and look at the
damage that iraq has done too
uh it's emboldened the iranians
we took out the only
the only thing that stood between iran
and the rest of the arabian gulf
saddam hussein was the only bulwark
against iranian hegemony
and we took him out for personal reasons
it made no geopolitical sense at all
and then when dick cheney went on tv and
tied muhammad atta
to saddam hussein specifically to the
iraqi uh intelligence service station
chief in prague
that was just a big lie out in outlaw
it was an out and out lie there was
absolutely no evidence
that muhammad atta ever met with any
representative of the iraqi government
it was made up and and it their
rationale
of they didn't care about this buffer of
iraq vis-a-vis around
because this was all about iran anyway
this was all about regime change in iran
and
it was i always leaved it yes yeah that
er that iraq was going to be the first
because in iraq once we cross the border
into iraq
they're going to throw flowers at us i
actually heard
a senior person on the national security
council say that in a video
teleconference
as soon as we cross the border they're
going to throw flowers at us
and i remember thinking are these people
insane
but first it was going to be iraq and
then it was going to be syria and then
it was going to be iran and we were
going to we were going to kick off
this democratic human rights loving wave
across the middle east beginning with
iraq all formed in a sea of blood
all formed in a sea of blood and hatched
in neoconservative think tanks in
washington
crazy stuff okay we'll pick it up in the
next segment please join us for the
continuation of reality asserts itself
with john kiriakou
on the real news network
[Music]
you